

CONTACT

TELEPHONE +52 442 3650800

EMAIL reginasanchez@cinvestav.mx

WEBSITE reginasanchez.github.io

ORCID 0000-0003-1506-6443

EDUCATION

PhD Materials Science CINVESTAV, Mexico 2013 – 2017

MS. Metallurgy and Materials Engineering UASLP, Mexico 2009 – 2011

BS. Chemical Engineering
UASLP, Mexico
2004 – 2008

REGINA SÁNCHEZ

PROFILE

My main interests are working on green processes for polymer synthesis, in particular biodegradable polymers and biopolymers.

I have worked over the last five years in projects involving the development of novel and sustainable approaches to polymer synthesis using *deep eutectic solvents* (DESs) – a class of solvents closely related to ionic liquids. Particularly, I have experience working on free-radical polymerization (by either using organic catalysts and enzymes), ring opening polymerization and oxidative polymerization in these non-conventional media for applications in controlled drug-release and clean energy conversion systems.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Nov 2015 – Institu Sept 2016 Bioins

Instituto de Ciencia de Materiales de Madrid

Bioinspired Materials Group

Spain

Synthesis and characterization of of conducting

polyaniline 3D structures prepared by

a novel approach using deep eutectic solvents for

applications in clean energy conversion.

Nov 2010 – Feb 2011 Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya

INTEXTER - Laboratory of Textile Polymers

Spain

Synthesis and characterization of poly(ethylene

terephthalate) – CaF_2 with focus on the study of the non-

isothermal crystallization behaviour of the material.

Apr 2009 – Aug 2009 Texas A&M University

The Artie McFerrin Department of

Chemical Engineering

USA

Research internship; bioethanol production from sugarcane bagasse with focus on the integration and

simulation process.

☐ SKILLS

Linux

Mac OS

Windows

Microsoft Office

LaTeX

Gnuplot

Inkscape

GIMP

A Z LANGUAGES

Spanish English

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

May 2018 – Research assistant

Present LANIMFE – Instituto de Física, UASLP

Mexico

Research and development of projects related to the

industrial sector.

ISO 9001:2015 implementation.

May 2017 - Research assistant

Sept 2017 CINVESTAV, Querétaro

Polymers & Biopolymers Group

Mexico

Enzymatic polymerization in deep eutectic solvents. Training and academic support to graduate students.

Sept 2011 – Technical assistant

Dec 2012 Instituto de Metalurgia – UASLP

Mexico

SEM and XRD analyses of mineral samples.

Technical support to the minerals research laboratory. Academic support to undergraduate and graduate

students.

FELLOWSHIPS & AWARDS

2018 SNI Level i Researcher

Awarded from the Mexican National Research System

Nov 2018 - Postdoctoral Fellowship

Oct 2019 Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute

Laboratory of Biocatalysis and Bioprocessing

USA

Granted by the Mexican National Council of Science and

Technology (CONACYT)

2018 MSCA – IF proposal Seal of Excellence

Awarded from the European Union within the H2020

Programme.

Nov 2015 - Doctoral stay Fellowship (CONACYT)

Sept 2016 Instituto de Ciencia de Materiales de Madrid

Spain

Jan 2013 – Doctoral Fellowship (CONACYT)

Jan 2016 CINVESTAV, Querétaro

Mexico

Nov 2010 - Master's stay Fellowship (CONACYT)

Feb 2011

Universitat Polytècnica de Catalunya INTEXTER – Laboratory of Textile Polymers Spain

Aug 2009 - Master's Fellowship (CONACYT) Aug 2011 Instituto de Metalurgia - UASLP

Mexico

Apr 2009 – Exchange Fellowship Aug 2009 – Texas A & M University

The Artie McFerrin Department of Chemical

Engineering

USA

Granted by the North American Mobility Program for Higher Education (NAMP), bilateral and trilateral program among Mexico, Canada and the United States with the goal of introducing process integration for environmental control in engineering curricula.

PUBLICATIONS

- Josué D. Mota-Morales, **Regina J. Sánchez-Leija**, Arturo Carranza, John A. Pojman, Francisco del Monte, Gabriel Luna-Bárcenas. *Prog. Polym. Sci.*, 2018, 78: 139–153.
- D. G. Ramírez-Wong, M. Ramírez-Cardona, R. J. Sánchez-Leija, A. Rugerio, R. A. Mauricio-Sánchez, M. A. Hernandez-Landaverde, A. Carranza, J. A. Pojman, A. M. Garay-Tapia, E. Prokhorov, J. D. Mota-Morales, G. Luna-Barcenas. Green Chem. 2016; 18: 4303–4311.
- R. J. Sánchez-Leija, J. R. Torres-Lubian, A. Resendiz-Rubio, G. Luna-Bárcenas, J. D. Mota-Morales. RSC Adv. 2016; 6: 13072–13079.
- R. J. Sánchez-Leija, J. A. Pojman, G. Luna-Bárcenas, J. D. Mota-Morales. J. Mater. Chem. B 2014; 2: 7495–7501.
- D. Cayuela, M. Cot, M. Riva, **R. J. Sánchez**, M. G. Sánchez-Loredo, I. Algaba, A. M. Manich. J. Macromol. Sci. Part A 2014; 51: 831–841.
- Regina Janet Sánchez-Leija, Marta Riba-Moliner, Diana Cayuela-Marín, Octavio Domínguez-Espinós, María Guadalupe Sánchez-Loredo. Polym. Eng. Sci. 2014; 54: 2938–2946.
- Regina Janet Sánchez-Leija, Marta Riba-Moliner, Diana Cayuela-Marín, Octavio Domínguez-Espinós, María Guadalupe Sánchez-Loredo. J. Macromol. Sci. Part B 2014; 53: 173–190.
- Feng Rao, Francisco J. Ramirez-Acosta, **Regina J. Sánchez-Leija**, Shaoxian Song, Alejandro López-Valdivieso. *Appl. Clay Sci.* 2011; 51: 38–42.

PARTICIPATION IN CONFERENCES

- "Sustainable polymer syntheses based on deep eutectic solvents". Annual Meeting of the Soft Condensed Matter Network (CONACyT), Qro., Mexico, August **2018** (Oral presentation).
- R. J. Sánchez-Leija, J. A. Pojman, G. Luna-Bárcenas, J. D. Mota-Morales. "Controlled release of lidocaine hydrochloride from polymerized drug-based deep eutectic solvents". 30th International Conference on Science and Technology of Complex Fluids, SLP, Mexico, June 2018 (Poster presentation).
- "Sustainable polymer syntheses bases on deep eutectic solvents". Research Seminars at the Faculty of Chemical Sciences UASLP, Mexico, February **2018**.
- "Deep eutectic solvents for green synthesis of polymers". Young Scientist Meetings at ICMM, Madrid, Spain, February **2016** (Oral presentation).
- R. J. Sánchez-Leija, J. R. Torres-Lubián, A. Resendiz-Rubio, G. Luna-Bárcenas, J. D. Mota-Morales. "Enzyme-mediated free-radical polymerization of acrylamide in deep eutectic solvents". 26th EUCHEM Conference on Molten Salts and Ionic Liquids in Vienna, Austria, July 2016 (Poster presentation)

RELEVANT TECHNICAL TRAINING

Course "Design of Pharmaceutical Solid Forms" Mexican Pharmaceutical Association, Mexico, July, 2014.

Course "Crystalline Structures by X-Ray Diffraction" Mexican Society of Crystallography, Mexico, June, 2014.

Workshop "Thinking about the ISO 9001: 2015 in my organization"

ISO Mexico Implementation Services, Mexico, September, 2018.